Some people say a science of consciousness is impossible. Science, by its nature, is objective. Consciousness, by its nature, is subjective. So there can never be a science of consciousness. For much of the 20th century, that view held sway. Psychologists studied behavior objectively, neuroscientists studied the brain objectively, and nobody even mentioned consciousness. Even 30 years ago, when TED got started, there was very little scientific work on consciousness. Now, about 20 years ago, all that began to change. Neuroscientists like Francis Crick and physicists like Roger Penrose said now is the time for science to attack consciousness. And since then, there's been a real explosion, a flowering of scientific work on consciousness. And this work has been wonderful. It's been great. But it also has some fundamental limitations so far.
Algunas personas dicen que es imposible una ciencia de la conciencia. La ciencia, por naturaleza, es objetiva. La conciencia, por naturaleza, es subjetiva. Entonces nunca puede existir una ciencia de la conciencia. Porque durante casi todo el siglo XX, predominó esa visión. La psicología estudiaba el comportamiento objetivamente, La neurociencia estudiaba el cerebro objetivamente, pero nunca nadie mencionó la conciencia. Incluso hace 30 años, cuando TED comenzó, había muy pocos trabajos científicos sobre la conciencia. Despues, hace 20 años, todo comenzó a cambiar. Neurocientíficos como Francis Crick y físicos como Roger Penrose dijeron: "ahora es el momento para que la ciencia aborde la conciencia". Y desde entonces, hubo una verdadera explosión, un florecimiento del trabajo científico sobre la conciencia. Y este trabajo fue fantástico. Fue genial. Pero también tiene limitaciones fundamentales hasta el momento.
The centerpiece of the science of consciousness in recent years has been the search for correlations, correlations between certain areas of the brain and certain states of consciousness. We saw some of this kind of work from Nancy Kanwisher and the wonderful work she presented just a few minutes ago. Now we understand much better, for example, the kinds of brain areas that go along with the conscious experience of seeing faces or of feeling pain or of feeling happy. But this is still a science of correlations. It's not a science of explanations. We know that these brain areas go along with certain kinds of conscious experience, but we don't know why they do. I like to put this by saying that this kind of work from neuroscience is answering some of the questions we want answered about consciousness, the questions about what certain brain areas do and what they correlate with. But in a certain sense, those are the easy problems. No knock on the neuroscientists. There are no truly easy problems with consciousness. But it doesn't address the real mystery at the core of this subject: why is it that all that physical processing in a brain should be accompanied by consciousness at all? Why is there this inner subjective movie? Right now, we don't really have a bead on that. And you might say, let's just give neuroscience a few years. It'll turn out to be another emergent phenomenon like traffic jams, like hurricanes, like life, and we'll figure it out. The classical cases of emergence are all cases of emergent behavior, how a traffic jam behaves, how a hurricane functions, how a living organism reproduces and adapts and metabolizes, all questions about objective functioning. You could apply that to the human brain in explaining some of the behaviors and the functions of the human brain as emergent phenomena: how we walk, how we talk, how we play chess, all these questions about behavior. But when it comes to consciousness, questions about behavior are among the easy problems. When it comes to the hard problem, that's the question of why is it that all this behavior is accompanied by subjective experience? And here, the standard paradigm of emergence, even the standard paradigms of neuroscience, don't really, so far, have that much to say. Now, I'm a scientific materialist at heart. I want a scientific theory of consciousness that works, and for a long time, I banged my head against the wall looking for a theory of consciousness in purely physical terms that would work. But I eventually came to the conclusion that that just didn't work for systematic reasons. It's a long story, but the core idea is just that what you get from purely reductionist explanations in physical terms, in brain-based terms, is stories about the functioning of a system, its structure, its dynamics, the behavior it produces, great for solving the easy problems — how we behave, how we function — but when it comes to subjective experience — why does all this feel like something from the inside? — that's something fundamentally new, and it's always a further question. So I think we're at a kind of impasse here. We've got this wonderful, great chain of explanation, we're used to it, where physics explains chemistry, chemistry explains biology, biology explains parts of psychology. But consciousness
El centro de la ciencia de la conciencia en los años recientes fue la búsqueda de correlaciones, correlaciones entre algunas áreas del cerebro y algunos estados de la conciencia. Vimos algo de este tipo en el fantástico trabajo que presentó Nancy Kanwisher hace unos minutos. Ahora entendemos mucho mejor, por ejemplo, las áreas del cerebro que están relacionadas con la experiencia consciente de ver caras o de sentir dolor o de sentirse feliz. Pero esta sigue siendo una ciencia de correlaciones. No es una ciencia de explicaciones. Sabemos que estas áreas del cerebro están relacionadas con ciertos tipos de experiencias conscientes, pero no sabemos por qué. Me gustaría explicarlo diciendo que este tipo de trabajo de la neurociencia responde algunas preguntas que queremos que explique la conciencia. Las preguntas sobre lo que hacen ciertas áreas del cerebro y con qué se correlacionan. Pero en un sentido, esos son los problemas fáciles, sin ofender a los neurocientíficos. En realidad, no hay problemas fáciles con la conciencia. Pues no aborda el verdadero misterio central de esta materia: ¿Por qué todo proceso físico en el cerebro tiene que estar acompañado por la conciencia? ¿Por qué existe una película interna subjetiva? En este momento, no lo podemos entender. Y Uds. pueden decir, démosle unos años a la neurociencia. Se va a convertir en otro fenómeno emergente como los embotellamientos, como los huracanes, como la vida, y vamos a encontrar explicación. Los surgimientos típicos son todos casos de comportamientos emergentes, cómo operan los embotellamientos, cómo funcionan los huracanes, cómo se reproducen, se adaptan y metabolizan los organismos vivos. Todas son preguntas sobre el funcionamiento objetivo. Eso se podría aplicar al cerebro humano para explicar algunos comportamientos y las funciones del cerebro humano como un fenómeno emergente: cómo caminamos, cómo hablamos, cómo jugamos ajedrez; todas son preguntas sobre el comportamiento. Pero cuando se trata de la conciencia, las preguntas sobre el comportamiento están entre los problemas fáciles. Pero el problema difícil, es la pregunta de ¿por qué es que todo comportamiento está acompañado de una experiencia subjetiva? Y aquí está, el paradigma estándar del surgimiento, el paradigma estándar de la neurociencia, en realidad todavía no tiene mucho que decir. Yo soy un materialista científico de corazón. Quiero una teoría científica de la autoreflexión que funcione. Durante mucho tiempo, me golpeaba la cabeza contra la pared buscando una teoría de la conciencia en puros términos físicos que funcionara. Pero al final llegué a la conclusión que eso no funcionaba por razones sistemáticas. Es una larga historia, pero la idea es que lo que consigues a partir de explicaciones puramente reduccionistas en términos físicos, en términos basados en el cerebro, son historias sobre el funcionamiento de un sistema; su estructura, su dinámica, el comportamiento que produce. Genial para resolver problemas fáciles: cómo nos comportamos, cómo funcionamos. Pero cuando se trata de experiencia subjetiva, ¿por qué todo se siente como si proviniera de adentro? Eso es algo fundamentalmente nuevo, y es siempre una pregunta para más adelante. Creo que nos estancamos en este punto. Tenemos una cadena de explicaciones maravillosa, genial. Nos acostumbramos a esto; la física explica la química, la química explica la biología, la biología explica parte de la psicología. Pero la conciencia
doesn't seem to fit into this picture. On the one hand, it's a datum that we're conscious. On the other hand, we don't know how to accommodate it into our scientific view of the world. So I think consciousness right now is a kind of anomaly, one that we need to integrate into our view of the world, but we don't yet see how. Faced with an anomaly like this, radical ideas may be needed, and I think that we may need one or two ideas that initially seem crazy before we can come to grips with consciousness scientifically. Now, there are a few candidates for what those crazy ideas might be. My friend Dan Dennett, who's here today, has one. His crazy idea is that there is no hard problem of consciousness. The whole idea of the inner subjective movie involves a kind of illusion or confusion. Actually, all we've got to do is explain the objective functions, the behaviors of the brain, and then we've explained everything that needs to be explained. Well I say, more power to him. That's the kind of radical idea that we need to explore if you want to have a purely reductionist brain-based theory of consciousness. At the same time, for me and for many other people, that view is a bit too close to simply denying the datum of consciousness to be satisfactory. So I go in a different direction. In the time remaining, I want to explore two crazy ideas that I think may have some promise. The first crazy idea is that consciousness is fundamental. Physicists sometimes take some aspects of the universe as fundamental building blocks: space and time and mass. They postulate fundamental laws governing them, like the laws of gravity or of quantum mechanics. These fundamental properties and laws aren't explained in terms of anything more basic. Rather, they're taken as primitive, and you build up the world from there. Now sometimes, the list of fundamentals expands. In the 19th century, Maxwell figured out that you can't explain electromagnetic phenomena in terms of the existing fundamentals — space, time, mass, Newton's laws — so he postulated fundamental laws of electromagnetism and postulated electric charge as a fundamental element that those laws govern. I think that's the situation we're in with consciousness. If you can't explain consciousness in terms of the existing fundamentals — space, time, mass, charge — then as a matter of logic, you need to expand the list. The natural thing to do is to postulate consciousness itself as something fundamental, a fundamental building block of nature. This doesn't mean you suddenly can't do science with it. This opens up the way for you to do science with it. What we then need is to study the fundamental laws governing consciousness, the laws that connect consciousness to other fundamentals: space, time, mass, physical processes. Physicists sometimes say that we want fundamental laws so simple that we could write them on the front of a t-shirt. Well I think something like that is the situation we're in with consciousness. We want to find fundamental laws so simple we could write them on the front of a t-shirt. We don't know what those laws are yet, but that's what we're after. The second crazy idea is that consciousness might be universal. Every system might have some degree of consciousness. This view is sometimes called panpsychism: pan for all, psych for mind, every system is conscious, not just humans, dogs, mice, flies, but even Rob Knight's microbes, elementary particles. Even a photon has some degree of consciousness. The idea is not that photons are intelligent or thinking. It's not that a photon is wracked with angst because it's thinking, "Aww, I'm always buzzing around near the speed of light. I never get to slow down and smell the roses." No, not like that. But the thought is maybe photons might have some element of raw, subjective feeling, some primitive precursor to consciousness. This may sound a bit kooky to you. I mean, why would anyone think such a crazy thing? Some motivation comes from the first crazy idea, that consciousness is fundamental. If it's fundamental, like space and time and mass, it's natural to suppose that it might be universal too, the way they are. It's also worth noting that although the idea seems counterintuitive to us, it's much less counterintuitive to people from different cultures, where the human mind is seen as much more continuous with nature. A deeper motivation comes from the idea that perhaps the most simple and powerful way to find fundamental laws connecting consciousness to physical processing is to link consciousness to information. Wherever there's information processing, there's consciousness. Complex information processing, like in a human, complex consciousness. Simple information processing, simple consciousness. A really exciting thing is in recent years a neuroscientist, Giulio Tononi, has taken this kind of theory and developed it rigorously with a mathematical theory. He has a mathematical measure of information integration which he calls phi, measuring the amount of information integrated in a system. And he supposes that phi goes along with consciousness. So in a human brain, incredibly large amount of information integration, high degree of phi, a whole lot of consciousness. In a mouse, medium degree of information integration, still pretty significant, pretty serious amount of consciousness. But as you go down to worms, microbes, particles, the amount of phi falls off. The amount of information integration falls off, but it's still non-zero. On Tononi's theory, there's still going to be a non-zero degree of consciousness. In effect, he's proposing a fundamental law of consciousness: high phi, high consciousness. Now, I don't know if this theory is right, but it's actually perhaps the leading theory right now in the science of consciousness, and it's been used to integrate a whole range of scientific data, and it does have a nice property that it is in fact simple enough you can write it on the front of a t-shirt. Another final motivation is that panpsychism might help us to integrate consciousness into the physical world. Physicists and philosophers have often observed that physics is curiously abstract. It describes the structure of reality using a bunch of equations, but it doesn't tell us about the reality that underlies it. As Stephen Hawking puts it, what puts the fire into the equations? Well, on the panpsychist view, you can leave the equations of physics as they are, but you can take them to be describing the flux of consciousness. That's what physics really is ultimately doing, describing the flux of consciousness. On this view, it's consciousness that puts the fire into the equations. On that view, consciousness doesn't dangle outside the physical world as some kind of extra. It's there right at its heart. This view, I think, the panpsychist view, has the potential to transfigure our relationship to nature, and it may have some pretty serious social and ethical consequences. Some of these may be counterintuitive. I used to think I shouldn't eat anything which is conscious, so therefore I should be vegetarian. Now, if you're a panpsychist and you take that view, you're going to go very hungry. So I think when you think about it, this tends to transfigure your views, whereas what matters for ethical purposes and moral considerations, not so much the fact of consciousness, but the degree and the complexity of consciousness. It's also natural to ask about consciousness in other systems, like computers. What about the artificially intelligent system in the movie "Her," Samantha? Is she conscious? Well, if you take the informational, panpsychist view, she certainly has complicated information processing and integration, so the answer is very likely yes, she is conscious. If that's right, it raises pretty serious ethical issues about both the ethics of developing intelligent computer systems and the ethics of turning them off. Finally, you might ask about the consciousness of whole groups, the planet. Does Canada have its own consciousness? Or at a more local level, does an integrated group like the audience at a TED conference, are we right now having a collective TED consciousness, an inner movie for this collective TED group which is distinct from the inner movies of each of our parts? I don't know the answer to that question, but I think it's at least one worth taking seriously. Okay, so this panpsychist vision, it is a radical one, and I don't know that it's correct. I'm actually more confident about the first crazy idea, that consciousness is fundamental, than about the second one, that it's universal. I mean, the view raises any number of questions, has any number of challenges, like how do those little bits of consciousness add up to the kind of complex consciousness we know and love. If we can answer those questions, then I think we're going to be well on our way to a serious theory of consciousness. If not, well, this is the hardest problem perhaps in science and philosophy. We can't expect to solve it overnight. But I do think we're going to figure it out eventually. Understanding consciousness is a real key, I think, both to understanding the universe and to understanding ourselves. It may just take the right crazy idea. Thank you. (Applause)
no parece encajar en este esquema. Por un lado, es un hecho que somos conscientes. Por otro, no sabemos cómo acomodar esa idea a nuestra visión científica del mundo. Creo que la conciencia, ahora mismo, es una especie de anomalía, algo que necesitamos integrar a nuestra visión del mundo, pero no sabemos todavía cómo. Con una anomalía como esta, se pueden necesitar ideas radicales. Creo que necesitamos ideas que al principio parecerán locas, antes de poder lidiar con la conciencia de una manera científica. Hay algunas posibilidades para esas ideas locas. Mi amigo Dan Dennett, que está aquí hoy, tiene una. Su idea loca es que no existe tal problema difícil de la conciencia. Toda la idea de la película subjetiva interna incluye una especie de ilusión o confusión. En realidad, lo que hay que hacer, es explicar las funciones objetivas, los comportamientos del cerebro. Y así se estudia todo lo que necesita explicación. Bueno, más poder para él. Ese es el tipo de idea radical que necesitamos explorar si queremos tener una teoría de la conciencia puramente reduccionista, basada en el cerebro. Al mismo tiempo, para mí y para muchos otros, esa visión está bastante cercana a simplemente negar que la observación de la conciencia sea satisfactoria. Pero yo voy en una dirección diferente. En el tiempo que queda, quiero explorar dos ideas locas que creo pueden ser prometedoras. La primera idea loca es que la conciencia es fundamental. Los físicos a veces toman algunos aspectos del universo como ladrillos fundamentales: el espacio, el tiempo y la masa. Postulan leyes fundamentales que los gobiernan, como las leyes de gravedad o de mecánica cuántica. Estas leyes y propiedades fundamentales no se explican en términos de nada más básico. Al contrario, se consideran fundamentales, y de ahí se construye el mundo. A veces, la lista de lo fundamental se alarga. En el siglo XIX Maxwell descubrió que no se pueden explicar los fenómenos electromagnéticos en términos de conceptos fundamentales preexistentes, espacio, tiempo, masa, leyes de Newton. Entonces postuló las leyes básicas del electromagnetismo. Y postuló la carga eléctrica como un concepto fundamental que esas leyes gobiernan. Creo que esa es la situación en que nos encontramos con la conciencia. Si no se puede explicar la conciencia en términos de ideas fundamentales preexistentes, espacio, tiempo, masa, carga, entonces por cuestión de lógica, hay que alargar la lista. Lo más natural sería postular la conciencia misma como algo fundamental, un ladrillo fundamental de la naturaleza. Esto no significa que de repente no sea objeto de la ciencia, sino que abre el camino para manejarla científicamente. Entonces lo que necesitamos es estudiar las leyes fundamentales que gobiernan la conciencia, las leyes que conectan la conciencia con otros conceptos fundamentales: el espacio, el tiempo, la masa, procesos físicos. Los físicos a veces dicen que queremos leyes fundamentales tan simples que las podamos estampar en una remera. La situación de la conciencia es algo así. Queremos encontrar leyes fundamentales tan simples que las podamos estampar en una camiseta. Todavía no sabemos qué leyes son, pero eso es lo que buscamos. La segunda idea loca es que la conciencia puede ser universal. Cada sistema puede tener un grado de conciencia. Esta visión a veces se llama panpsiquismo: "Pan" por todos, "psiqui" por mente, cada sistema es consciente, no solamente los humanos, los perros, los ratones, las moscas, incluso los microbios de Rob Knight, las partículas elementales. Incluso un fotón tiene algún grado de conciencia. La idea no es que los fotones sean inteligentes o que piensen. No es que un fotón pueda estar lleno de angustia cuando piensa "Ay, siempre viajando a la velocidad de la luz. Nunca puedo desacelerar y oler las rosas". No, así no. Pero el pensamiento es que quizás los fotones pueden tener algún elemento de sentimiento crudo, subjetivo, algún precursor primitivo de la conciencia. Esto puede sonar un poco loco para Uds. ¿Cómo alguien pensaría algo tan loco? En parte esto proviene de la primera idea loca, que la conciencia es algo fundamental. Si es fundamental, como el espacio, el tiempo y la masa, es natural suponer que también puede ser universal, igual que los otros. También vale la pena notar que aunque la idea nos parece ilógica, lo es mucho menos para las personas de culturas diferentes, donde la mente humana parece más un continuo con la naturaleza. Una razón más profunda proviene de la idea de que quizás la forma más simple y poderosa de encontrar leyes fundamentales que relacionen el pensamiento con el proceso físico, es vinculando la conciencia con la información. Siempre que hay procesamiento de información, hay conciencia. Procesamiento de infomación compleja, como en un ser humano, conciencia compleja. Procesamiento de información simple, conciencia simple. Algo muy emocionante es que en los años recientes un neurocientífico, Giulio Tononi, tomó este tipo de teoría y la desarrolló rigurosamente con métodos matemáticos. Tiene una medida matemática de integración de la información, que llama phi, que mide el grado de información integrada en un sistema. Y supone que phi tiene que ver con la conciencia. Entonces en un cerebro humano, hay un increíble grado alto de integración de información, un grado alto de phi, mucha conciencia. En un ratón hay un grado medio de integración de información, igual bastante significativo, grado de conciencia bastante importante. Pero cuando se llega a las lombrices, microbios, partículas, el grado de phi decae. El nivel de integración de información es menor, pero no es cero tampoco. En la teoría de Tononi, todavía habrá un nivel de conciencia diferente de cero. De hecho propone una ley fundamental de la conciencia: alto grado de phi, alto grado de conciencia. No se si esta teoría es correcta, pero es probablemente la principal teoría en este momento en la ciencia de la conciencia. Se utiliza para integrar toda la gama de información científica. Tiene una buena propiedad que, de hecho, es lo suficientemente simple como para estamparla en una camiseta. Además, otra razón es que el panpsiquismo puede ayudarnos a integrar la conciencia al mundo físico. Los físicos y los filósofos con frecuencia han observado que la física es curiosamente abstracta. Describe la estructura de la realidad usando un montón de ecuaciones, pero no nos habla sobre la realidad que subyace debajo. Como explica Stephen Hawking, "¿De dónde sale el fuego de las ecuaciones?" Desde la visión panpsíquica las ecuaciones de la física se pueden dejar como están, pero se pueden usar para describir el flujo de la conciencia. Eso es lo que los físicos hacen básicamente, describen el flujo de la conciencia. Según esta visión, la conciencia es la que le pone fuego en las ecuaciones. En esa visión, la conciencia no se encuentra fuera del mundo físico como una especie de aditivo. Está ahí mismo en el centro. Esta visión, creo, la visión panpsíquica, tiene el potencial para transfigurar nuestra relación con la naturaleza, y puede tener consecuencias sociales y éticas bastante serias. Algunas pueden ser ilógicas. Yo solía pensar que no debía comer nada que tuviera conciencia, entonces debía ser vegetariano. Si eres un panpsíquico y aceptas esa visión, tendrás mucha hambre. Creo que pensándolo bien, esto tiende a transformar tus visiones, mientras que lo que importa en términos éticos y consideraciones morales, no es tanto el hecho de la conciencia, sino su importancia y su complejidad. También es natural preguntar por la conciencia en otros sistemas, como las computadoras. ¿Qué hay sobre el sistema de inteligencia artificial de Samantha en la película "Her"? ¿Es consciente? Según la visión de la información panpsíquica, ella tiene un procesamiento de información complicado, integrado, de modo que la respuesta es sí, si es consciente. Si esto es correcto, se plantean problemas éticos bastante serios sobre la ética del desarrollo de sistemas de computadoras inteligentes y la ética de apagarlos. Finalmente, Uds. pueden preguntar por la conciencia de colectivos completos, el planeta. ¿Canadá tiene su propia conciencia? O a un nivel más local, ¿un grupo integrado, como la audiencia en una charla TED. ¿En este momento tenemos una conciencia colectiva TED, una película interna para este grupo completo de TED, distinta de las películas internas de cada una de las partes? No sé la respuesta a esa pregunta, pero creo que al menos es una pregunta que debe tomarse en serio. Entonces esta vision panpsíquica, es una visión radical, y no sé si es correcta. En realidad estoy más seguro de la primer idea loca, que la conciencia es algo fundamental, que de la segunda, de que sea universal. La visión plantea muchas preguntas, muchos desafíos, como, cómo esos pedacitos de pensamiento contribuyen al tipo de conciencia compleja que conocemos y nos encanta. Si podemos responder a esas preguntas, entonces creo que vamos por el camino correcto hacia una teoría de la conciencia seria. Si no, bueno, probablemente éste es el problema más difícil de la ciencia y de la filosofía. No podemos esperar resolverlo de la noche a la mañana. Pero creo que finalmente lo iremos a descubrir. Entender la conciencia es la verdadera clave, creo, para entender el universo y para entendernos a nosotros mismos. Quizás sólo necesitemos la idea loca correcta. Gracias. (Aplausos)